In the last video we talked
前回のビデオで
about the Multivariate Gaussian Distribution
多変量ガウス分布を議論した。
and saw some examples of the
そしてパラメータのミューとシグマを変えていく事で
sorts of distributions you can model, as
モデリング出来る分布の例を
you vary the parameters, mu and sigma.
幾つか見た。
In this video, let's take those
このビデオでは、それらのアイデアを用いて、
ideas, and apply them
別のアノマリー検出のアルゴリズムを
to develop a different anomaly detection algorithm.
開発していこう。
To recap the multivariate Gaussian
復習しておくと、多変量ガウス分布、またの名を
distribution and the multivariate normal
多変量正規分は、
distribution has two parameters, mu and sigma.
二つのパラメータ、ミューとシグマを持っている。
Where mu this an n
ここでミューは
dimensional vector and sigma,
n次元ベクトルで、
the covariance matrix, is an
シグマ、共分散行列は、
n by n matrix.
n掛けるn行列。
And here's the formula for
そしてこれがxの確率の
the probability of X, as
式である、
parameterized by mu and
ミューとシグマでパラメトライズされた。
sigma, and as you
そしてミューとシグマを
vary mu and sigma, you
変更していく事で、
can get a range of different
あなたは様々な範囲の分布を
distributions, like, you know,
得る事が出来る、
these are three examples of the
例えばこれら三つの例は
ones that we saw in the previous video.
我らが前回のビデオで見た、そんな物の中の一例だ。
So let's talk about the
ではパラメータのフィッティングについて
parameter fitting or the
議論しよう、言い換えると
parameter estimation problem. The
パラメータ推計の問題について。
question, as usual, is if
問いは、いつも通り、
I have a set of examples
x1からxmまでの手本の集合が
X1 through XM and here each
あったとして、そしてここでは
of these examples is an
これらの手本はおのおの
n dimensional vector and I think my
n次元ベクトルで、
examples come from a multivariate Gaussian distribution.
そしてこの手本は多変量ガウス分布の分布に従っている、と思ったとする。
How do I try to estimate my parameters mu and sigma?
どうやってパラメータ、ミューとシグマを推計したらいいだろうか？
Well the standard formulas for
それらを推計する
estimating them is you
標準的な公式は、
set mu to be just
ミューにトレーニング手本の
the average of your training examples.
平均をセットすれば良い。
And you set sigma to be equal to this.
そしてシグマにはイコールこれを。
And this is actually just
これは実際に、
like the sigma that we had
PCA、あるいは主成分分析を
written out, when we were
使った時に
using the PCA or
我らが書き下した物と
the Principal Components Analysis algorithm.
同様の物だ。
So you just plug in these
さて、これら二つの式に
two formulas and this
代入するだけで、
would give you your estimated parameter
推計されたパラメータ、ミューと、
mu and your estimated parameter sigma.
推計されたパラメータのシグマが得られる。
So given the data set here is how you estimate mu and sigma.
つまりデータセットが与えられた時に、ミューとシグマを推計する方法だ。
Let's take this method
ではこの手法を
and just plug it
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムに
into an anomaly detection algorithm.
組み込んでみよう。
So how do we
では、どうやったら
put all of this together to
我らはこれらを全て組み合わせて
develop an anomaly detection algorithm?
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムを開発出来るだろうか？
Here 's what we do.
我らがやるべきは、こうだ。
First we take our training
まず、トレーニングセットに対し、
set, and we fit the
モデルをフィッティングする、
model, we fit P
p(x)をフィッティングする、
of X, by, you know, setting
前のスライドで記述した
mu and sigma as described
ミューとシグマを
on the previous slide.
設定する事で。
Next when you are given
次に、新しい手本xが
a new example X. So
与えられた時に、
if you are given a test example,
テストの手本が与えられたとすると、、、
lets take an earlier example to have a new example out here.
前の例から、新しい手本をここに得たとしよう。
And that is my test example.
これが私のテスト手本。
Given the new example X, what
新しい手本xが与えられた時に、
we are going to do is compute
我らがやる事は、p(x)を計算する事、
P of X, using this
この多変量ガウス分布の式を
formula for the multivariate Gaussian distribution.
用いる事で。
And then, if P of
そして次に、
X is very small, then we
p(x)がとても小さかったら、
flagged it as an anomaly,
それをアノマリーとフラグ立てする。
whereas, if P of X is greater
他方、p(x)がパラメータのイプシロンより
than that parameter epsilon, then
大きければ、
we don't flag it as an anomaly.
それにはアノマリーのフラグは立てない。
So it turns out, if we were to fit a multivariate Gaussian distribution to this data set,
つまり結局、もしこのデータセットに多変量ガウス分布をフィッティングするとすると、
so just the red crosses, not the green example,
このデータセットというのは赤のクロスで、緑の手本は含まないが、
you end up with a Gaussian
そうすると結局、
distribution that places lots
以下のようなガウス分布が得られる：
of probability in the central
中心の領域にたくさんの確率を、
region, slightly less probability here,
ここにはちょっとだけ低い確率を、
slightly less probability here,
ここにはさらにちょっとだけ低い確率を、
and very low probability at the point that is way out here.
そしてここより外はとても低い確率となるような物だ。
And so, if you apply
つまり、この例で
the multivariate Gaussian distribution to
多変量ガウス分布を
this example, it will actually
適用すると、これは実際に
correctly flag that example.
ただしくこの手本をフラグ立てする、
as an anomaly.
アノマリーだと。
Finally it's worth saying
最後に、多変量ガウス分布モデルと
a few words about what is
元のモデルとの間の関係について
the relationship between the
2, 3言っておく
multivariate Gaussian distribution model, and
価値があるだろう、
the original model, where we
ここで元のモデルとは、
were modeling P of
p(x)を
X as a product of this
p(x1), p(x2), ..., p(xn)までの
P of X1, P of X2,
積でモデリング
up to P of Xn.
したもの。
It turns out that you can
以下の事が数学的に証明出来る事が
prove mathematically, I'm not
知られている。
going to do the proof here, but
ここで証明はしないが。
you can prove mathematically that this
だが、多変量ガウス分布のモデルと
relationship, between the
オリジナルのモデルの間の
multivariate Gaussian model and
この関係を
this original one. And in
数学的に証明する事が出来る。
particular, it turns out
より詳細には、
that the original model corresponds
オリジナルのモデルは、
to multivariate Gaussians, where
多変量ガウス分布の、ガウス分布の等高線が
the contours of the
いつも軸に沿っている場合に対応している事が
Gaussian are always axis aligned.
知られている。
So all three of
つまり、これら三つは全て
these are examples of
オリジナルのモデルを使って
Gaussian distributions that you
フィッティングする事が可能な
can fit using the original model.
ガウス分布の例だ。
It turns out that that corresponds
これは結局、
to multivariate Gaussian, where, you
多変量ガウス分布のうち、
know, the ellipsis here, the contours
この楕円、
of this distribution--it
分布の等高線が、、、
turns out that this model actually
このモデルは実際に
corresponds to a special
多変量ガウス分布の
case of a multivariate Gaussian distribution.
特別なケースに対応している。
And in particular, this special
具体的には、この特別なケースとは、
case is defined by constraining
p(x)の分布、
the distribution of p
多変量ガウス分布としてのp(x)の分布を、
of x, the multivariate a Gaussian
確率密度関数の、、、
distribution of p of x,
確率分布関数の等高線を
so that the contours of
軸に沿った物に
the probability density function, of
制限した物、として
the probability distribution function, are axis aligned.
定義する事が出来る。
And so you can get a p
つまり多変量ガウス分布の
of x with a
p(x)として、
multivariate Gaussian that looks like
このような物や、
this, or like this, or like this.
このような物、またはこのような物を、得る事が出来る。
And you notice, that in all
そして見て分かるように、
3 of these examples, these ellipses,
これら三つは全て、これらの楕円は、
or these ovals that I'm drawing, have
または私が今描いた楕円は、
their axes aligned with the X1 X2 axes.
その軸がx1 x2軸に沿っている。
And what we do not have, is
そして我らが持っていない物として、
a set of contours
角度のある等高線の
that are at an angle, right?
集合だ。でしょ？
And this corresponded to examples where
そしてこの事は、シグマがイコール
sigma is equal to 1 1, 0.8, 0.8.
1, 1とか0.8, 0.8などの例に対応した物で、
Let's say, with non-0 elements on the
非対角成分に非0成分が
off diagonals.
存在していないという事。
So, it turns out that
つまり、このモデルは
it's possible to show mathematically that
実際に多変量ガウス分布に
this model actually is the
制約を加えた物である、という事を
same as a multivariate Gaussian
数学的に証明出来る事が
distribution but with a constraint.
知られている。
And the constraint is that the
そしてその制約とは、
covariance matrix sigma must
共分散行列のシグマは
have 0's on the off diagonal elements.
非対角成分が0でなくてはならない、とい事だ。
In particular, the covariance matrix sigma,
具体的に言うと、共分散行列シグマは
this thing here, it would
ここのこれは、
be sigma squared 1, sigma
シグマ二乗1、シグマ二乗2,、、、と
squared 2, down to sigma
シグマ二乗nまでと、
squared n, and then
そしてそれ以外の全ての
everything on the off diagonal
非対角成分の要素は、
entries, all of these elements
行列の、対角線より上側のこれら全てと、
above and below the diagonal of the matrix,
下側のこれら全て、
all of those are going to be zero.
それら全てが、ゼロとなる。
And in fact if you take
そして実際、もしこれらの
these values of sigma, sigma
シグマの値、
squared 1, sigma squared 2,
シグマ二乗の1, シグマ二乗の2,...と
down to sigma squared n,
シグマ二乗のnまでの値を、
and plug them into here, and
ここに代入して、
you know, plug them into this
この共分散行列に
covariance matrix, then the
代入すると、
two models are actually identical.
二つのモデルは、実際に同一となる。
That is, this new model,
つまり、この新しいモデル、
using a multivariate Gaussian distribution,
多変量ガウス分布を用いたこのモデルは、
corresponds exactly to the
古いモデルと厳密に一致する、
old model, if the covariance
もし非対角成分が
matrix sigma, has only
全てゼロとなるような
0 elements off the diagonals,
共分散行列のシグマの場合には。
and in pictures that
それは具体的には、
corresponds to having Gaussian distributions,
ガウス分布のうち、
where the contours of this
この分布関数の等高線が
distribution function are axis aligned.
軸に沿っている物に対応している。
So you aren't allowed to model the correlations between the diffrent features.
だから異なるフィーチャー間の相関をモデリングする事は許されていない。
So in that sense the original model
つまりその意味で、オリジナルのモデルは、
is actually a special case of this multivariate Gaussian model.
実際に多変量ガウス分布のモデルの特別な場合となっている。
So when would you use each of these two models?
では、どういう場合に、これら二つのモデルのどちらを使ったらいいか？
So when would you the original
つまりあなたはいつ、オリジナルのモデルを使うべきで、
model and when would you use
そしてあなたはいつ、多変量ガウス分布のモデルを
the multivariate Gaussian model?
使うべきなのだろうか？
The original model is probably
オリジナルのモデルは、
used somewhat more often,
おそらくより頻繁に用いられるだろう、
and whereas the multivariate Gaussian
一方で多変量ガウス分布はおそらく
distribution is used somewhat
より少ししか用いられないだろう、
less but it has the advantage of being
だがそちらの方には、フィーチャー間の相関を
able to capture correlations between features. So
捉える事が出来る、という利点がある。
suppose you want to
つまり、例えば
capture anomalies where you
異なるフィーチャー同士、
have different features say where
ここではフィーチャーx1, x2としよう、
features x1, x2 take
これらのフィーチャー同士の
on unusual combinations of values
異常な組み合わせの値となるアノマリーを検出したいとしよう、
so in the earlier
つまり前の例で言うと、
example, we had that example where the anomaly was with the CPU load and the memory use taking on unusual combinations of values, if
CPUロードとメモリ使用量が異常な値の組み合わせとなっているアノマリーの手本があった。
you want to use the original
もしオリジナルのモデルを使って
model to capture that, then what you
これを捉えたいと思えば、
need to do is create an
あなたはこんな追加のフィーチャーを
extra feature, such as X3
作る必要がある、それは
equals X1/X2, you know
例えば x3=x1/x2 みたいな。
equals maybe the CPU load divided by the memory used, or something, and you
つまりイコール、(CPUロード)/(メモリ使用量) とかみたいな。
need to create extra features
つまり、追加のフィーチャーとして、
if there's unusual combinations of values
x1とx2が異常な
where X1 and X2 take
組み合わせの値となる時は、
on an unusual combination of
たとえx1単体とx2単体で見た場合に
values even though X1 by
どちらも完全に正常だとしても、
itself and X2 by itself
異常な値となる追加のフィーチャーを
looks like it's taking a perfectly normal value. But if you're willing to spend the time to manually
作り出す必要がある。 だが、もしこのような追加のフィーチャーを
create an extra feature like this,
作る事に喜んで時間を差し出せるなら、
then the original model will work
オリジナルなモデルはちゃんと機能するだろう。
fine. Whereas in contrast, the multivariate Gaussian model can automatically capture
一方、対照的に、多変量ガウス分布のモデルは、自動的に
correlations between different features. But the original model has some other more significant advantages, too, and one huge
フィーチャー同士の相関を捉える事が出来る。 しかしオリジナルのモデルには、他にも重要な利点がある。
advantage of the original model
そんな利点のうち大きな物としては、
is that it is computationally cheaper, and another view on this
オリジナルのモデルの方が計算量的に安上がりだ、という事。 これを別の見方をすると、
is that is scales better to
これは非常に大きなnの値に、
very large values of n
つまり非常に大きなフィーチャーの数に
and very large numbers of
より良くスケールする。
features, and so even
だから、たとえ
if n were ten thousand,
nが1万とか、
or even if n were equal
またはnが10万とかでも、
to a hundred thousand, the original
オリジナルのモデルは
model will usually work just fine.
割と普通に動く。
Whereas in contrast for the multivariate Gaussian model notice here, for
他方、対照的に多変量ガウス分布のモデルでは、例えばここを見ると、
example, that we need to
行列シグマの逆行列を
compute the inverse of the matrix
計算する必要があり、
sigma where sigma is
このシグマは
an n by n matrix
n掛けるn行列だ。
and so computing sigma if
つまり、シグマで計算する時には、
sigma is a hundred thousand by a
シグマが 10万掛ける10万 の行列の時には、
hundred thousand matrix that is going to be very computationally expensive.
計算量的にとても高価になってしまう。
And so the multivariate Gaussian model
つまり、多変量ガウス分布のモデルは、
scales less well to large
大きなnの値に対しては、
values of N. And
相対的には、よりいまいちスケールしない。
finally for the original
そして最後に、オリジナルの方のモデルでは、
model, it turns out
たとえトレーニングセットが
to work out ok even if
相対的に小さくても、
you have a relatively small training
うまく機能する事が分かっている。
set this is the small unlabeled
これはp(x)をモデリングする時に用いる
examples that we use to model p of x
ラベル無しのトレーニング手本が小さくても、
of course, and this works fine, even if
うまく機能する、
M is, you
たとえmが、
know, maybe 50, 100, works fine.
50とか100でも、たぶんうまく機能する。
Whereas for the multivariate Gaussian, it
他方、多変量ガウシアンでは、
is sort of a mathematical property
アルゴリズムにある種の数学的な
of the algorithm that you must have m
性質があって、mはnより大きくないといけない。
greater than n, so that the number of examples is greater than the number of features you have. And there's a mathematical property of the way we estimate the parameters
つまり、手本の数は、フィーチャーの数よりは大きくないといけない。
that if this is not true, so if m is less than or equal to n,
もしこれが真で無いと、つまりmがn以下だと、
then this matrix isn't even invertible, that is this matrix is singular, and so you can't even use the
この行列が可逆じゃなくなる、つまりこの行列が特異行列となり、何かしら変更しないと
multivariate Gaussian model unless you make some changes to it. But a
多変量ガウス分布のモデルは、使う事すら出来ない。
typical rule of thumb
だけど典型的なルールとしての経験則として
that I use is, I will use the
私が採用しているのは、
multivariate Gaussian model only if m is much greater than n, so this is sort of the
私はmがnよりもずっと大きい時しか多変量ガウス分布は使わない、という物。
narrow mathematical requirement, but
つまりこれは、実際的な物よりちょっと狭い数学的な要求と言える。
in practice, I would use
実際には、私は
the multivariate Gaussian model, only
多変量ガウス分布のモデルは、
if m were quite a bit
mがかなりnより大きい時しか
bigger than n. So if
使わない。
m were greater than or
例えばmが 10掛けるn
equal to 10 times n, let's
以上なら、とかは、
say, might be a reasonable rule of thumb, and if
リーズナブルな経験則と言えそう。
it doesn't satisfy this, then the multivariate Gaussian model
そしてこれを満たしていなければ、、、多変量ガウス分布のモデルが
has a lot
たくさんのパラメータを持っていると、
of parameters, right, so this covariance matrix sigma is an n by n matrix,
この共分散行列シグマはn掛けるn行列なので、
so it has, you know, roughly
これはだいたいn二乗のパラメータを持つ、
n squared parameters, because it's a symmetric matrix,
これは対称行列だから、
it's actually closer to n squared
実際は n二乗割る2 に近いくらいの
over 2 parameters, but this is a
パラメータだが。
lot of parameters, so you need
だが、これは大量のパラメータだ。
make sure you have a fairly
だからかなり大きな値のmがあるという事を保証しておく必要がある。
large value for m, make sure you have enough data to fit all these parameters. And m greater than
これらのパラメータの全てにフィッティングするだけの、十分なデータがある事を保証しておく必要がある。
or equal to 10 n would be a reasonable rule of thumb to make sure that you can estimate this covariance matrix sigma reasonably well.
そこでmが10n以上、というのは、この共分散行列を推計出来る為の、リーズナブルな経験則と言えるだろう。
So in practice the original
さて、実践の場では、
model shown on the left that is used more often.
左に示したオリジナルのモデルの方が、より頻繁に使われる。
And if you suspect that you
そしてもしあなたが、フィーチャー同士の相関を
need to capture correlations between features
捉える必要があるんじゃないか、と思っているなら、
what people will often do is just manually design extra features like these to capture specific
そういう時は人々はよく、単に人力でそれらの異常な値の組み合わせを捉える
unusual combinations of values. But in problems where you
追加のフィーチャーをデザインする、という事をする。 だが、とても大量のトレーニングセットを持っていて、
have a very large training set or m is very large and n is
つまりmがとても大きくて、そしてnがそんなに大きく無いような問題に
not too large, then the multivariate Gaussian
直面している時は、多変量ガウス分布のモデルは、
model is well worth considering and may work better as well, and can
検討してみる価値があり、よりうまく機能する事もあり、
save you from having to
異常なフィーチャーの値の組を
spend your time to manually
捉える結果となるような
create extra features in case
追加のフィーチャーを
the anomalies turn out to be captured by unusual
人力で作るのに時間を費やさずに
combinations of values of the features.
済ます事が出来るかもしれない。
Finally I just want to
最後に、いくらかテクニカルな性質だが、
briefly mention one somewhat technical
ちょっと簡単に触れておきたい事がある。
property, but if you're
多変量ガウス分布の
fitting multivariate Gaussian
モデルをフィッティングする時に、
model, and if you find
もし共分散行列のシグマが
that the covariance matrix sigma
特異行列だと
is singular, or you find
見出したら、あるいはそれが非可逆だと
it's non-invertible, they're usually 2 cases for this.
見出したら、それには普通、二つの場合がある。
One is if it's failing to
一つ目は、
satisfy this m greater than
このmがnより大きい、という条件を
n condition, and the
満たしていない場合。
second case is if you have redundant features.
二番目は、冗長なフィーチャーがある場合。
So by redundant features, I mean,
冗長なフィーチャーという言葉で私が意味している事は、
if you have 2 features that are the same.
同一のフィーチャーが二つある、という事。
Somehow you accidentally made two
どうにかして、偶然二つのコピーのフィーチャーを作ってしまった、つまり
copies of the feature, so your x1 is just equal to x2. Or if you have redundant features like maybe
x1は単に、イコールx2であるようなフィーチャーを作ってしまった、だとか、あるいは例えば
your features X3 is equal to feature X4, plus feature X5.
フィーチャーx3 = フィーチャーx4+フィーチャーx5 のような冗長なフィーチャーがあるという場合。
Okay, so if you have highly
オーケー。で、このような
redundant features like these, you
とても冗長なフィーチャーがある場合、
know, where if X3 is equal
もしx3=x4+x5なら、
to X4 plus X5, well X3
x3は何も追加の情報を
doesn't contain any extra information, right?
含んでいない。
You just take these 2 other features, and add them together.
単にこれら二つの別のフィーチャーを、足し合わせるだけだ。
And if you have this
そしてもしあなたがこの手の冗長な、
sort of redundant features, duplicated features,
重複したフィーチャーとかこの種のフィーチャーを
or this sort of features, than sigma may be non-invertible.
保持している時には、シグマは非可逆になってしまう。
And so there's a debugging set--
以上はデバッギングの時の豆知識だ。
this should very rarely happen,
これは本当に稀にしか起こらないはずで、
so you probably won't run into this,
だからあなたが鉢合わせする事も多分無いだろう。
it is very unlikely that you have to worry about this--
これは、あなたが心配するにはあまりにもレア過ぎる。
but in case you implement a
だがあなたが多変量ガウス分布のモデルを
multivariate Gaussian model you find that sigma is non-invertible.
実装してみて、シグマが非可逆だという事を発見したら、
What I would do is first
私だったらまず、
make sure that M is quite
mがnよりもずっと大きい事を
a bit bigger than N, and if it
確認し、もしそうであるなら、次に
is then, the second thing I
二番目に私がやる事は、
do, is just check for redundant features.
冗長なフィーチャーをチェックする事だ。
And so if there are 2 features
そして、もし単純に等しい二つのフィーチャーが
that are equal, just get rid
ある時には、
of one of them, or if
一方を取り除けば良い。
you have redundant if these
そしてもしx3=x4+x5のような
, X3 equals X4 plus X5,
冗長なフィーチャーがある時には、
just get rid of the redundant
その冗長なフィーチャーを取り除けば良い。
feature, and then it should work fine again.
そうすればまた正常に機能するようになるだろう。
As an aside for those of you
線形代数のエキスパートの聴衆の為に
who are experts in linear algebra,
ちょっと脇道に逸れると、
by redundant features, what I
冗長なフィーチャー、という言葉で
mean is the formal term is
私が意味している事の正式な用語は、
features that are linearly dependent.
フィーチャーが線形に従属している、という事。
But in practice what that really means
だが実践に際しては、それが実際に意味している事は、
is one of these problems tripping
これらの問題の一つがアルゴリズムをつまづかせていたら、
up the algorithm if you just make you features non-redundant.,
あなたはフィーチャーを冗長では無くすだけで、
that should solve the problem of sigma being non-invertable.
シグマが非可逆、という問題を解決出来るはずだ。
But once again
だがもう一度繰り返しておくと
the odds of your running into this
あなたが生涯でこの問題に遭遇するという事象に対するオッズは
at all are pretty low so
極めて低い。だから、
chances are, you can
おそらくあなたは、
just apply the multivariate Gaussian
mがnより大きい、という事さえ注意しておけば、
model, without having to
多変量ガウス分布のモデルを
worry about sigma being non-invertible,
シグマが非可逆である、という事を心配する事無く
so long as m is greater
適用する事が
than or equal to n. So
出来るだろう。
that's it for anomaly detection,
さて、以上が多変量ガウス分布による
with the multivariate Gaussian distribution.
アノマリー検出だ。
And if you apply this method
そしてこの手法を適用すれば、
you would be able to have an
あなたのフィーチャー間での
anomaly detection algorithm that automatically
正や負の相関を自動で捉えるような
captures positive and negative
アノマリー検出の
correlations between your different
アルゴリズムを得る事が出来、
features and flags an anomaly
そしてフィーチャーの値の組み合わせが
if it sees is unusual combination
異常なのを目撃したら、
of the values of the features.
アノマリーだとフラグを立てる事が出来る。